The word "guru" comes from
"the one which is magnetic,
the person who is magnetic";
the one which attracts the attention of the seekers
is the guru. Also it means
the heaviness, or you can say,
a person who is very steady,
who is very deep, who has the knowledge,
and who can act like the Mother Earth.
For the power of magnetism in the Mother Earth
also is called as magnetic,
but in Sanskrit is "Gurutwa karshan,"
means "the attraction
of the heaviness of the Mother Earth."
But actually it is
a power of the Mother Earth that makes us stand
properly on our legs when it is rotating
with such a tremendous speed,
otherwise we would be all thrown away.
With that velocity that She is moving,
we are still attached or we are one in our balance,
is only because She has gravity.
This gravity has to be in a guru.
Gravity means
a kind of a serious understanding of oneself
and one's own responsibilities.
So a guru has to be very steady.
In these modern times, people are very mobile,
all the time agitated,
all the time getting disturbed.
With small things happening here and there, they get disturbed.
They meet people who are not of any quality,
then they get disturbed.
These disturbing qualities
come from our deficiency in our gravity.
A person who has gravity doesn't get depressed,
neither get excited,
nor get overly enthusiastic,
nor is he very sad or unhappy.
So he's in the center,
he's in the center of his being.
But how do we become the guru?
That is very important for Sahaja Yogis to understand.
Many have felt that they are gurus,
they have tried to behave in a funny manner,
and have lost their guru position.
First and foremost thing for Sahaja Yogis,
it is important that they must have introspection,
they must watch themselves.
If a person runs about
changing because a fashion has come,
because people have suppressed them, or have asked them;
just to please people of cheap values,
if a person changes, then he cannot be a guru.
He has to station himself
properly on the values of Sahaja Yoga.
Without introspection you will not know,
you will never remember what you have done wrong,
nor will you think of what you have to do right.
But that is only possible if you go on improving yourself.
First and foremost thing is,
all the great saints have praised their guru.
For example, we have a very great saint,
Gyaneshwara, in India.
He's written a complete chapter about the guru.
In English they have translated it as "preceptor" -
guru is the preceptor -
and what he has done is a great thing.
He says you are not to challenge the guru,
otherwise you can never become a guru;
for name's sake you might be, but you are not.
Secondly, you can never misbehave.
You can never be rude, arrogant,
and you cannot show your temper to a guru.
If that is so, that means you are not a guru,
you are still on a very low level personality.
It is very clearly said
that if you try to say against other gurus
who are real gurus, who are very high caliber,
that also, then you are not a guru.
But I would say that you all have got now vibrations,
you all have got vibratory awareness.